Guide to the Margaret Bonds Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Margaret Bonds papers
1928-1983
1960-1969
JWJ MSS 151
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.87
(13 boxes)
Vocal music, most 1960s or undated, consisting of autograph manuscript drafts and arrangements, transparencies, and diazo reproductions, some accompanied by copies of published music; and a small amount of other papers. Autograph manuscript music includes spirituals arranged for solo voice or chorus; The Negro Speaks of Rivers, Songs of the Seasons, Three Dream Portraits, and other songs on texts by Langston Hughes; songs on texts by Edna St. Vincent Millay and other poets; and musicals and songs with lyrics by Janice Lovoos, some with related correspondence. Other papers consist of a scrapbook containing photographs, clippings, and ephemera, most circa 1928-1930, some relating to Lincoln University, Pennsylvania, and Lawrence Richardson; and two books containing biographical information about Bonds and analysis of her music: Mildred Denby Green, Black Women Composers: A Genesis (Boston: Twayne Publishers, 1983), and Alice Tischler, Fifteen Black American Composers: A Bibliography of Their Works (Detroit: Information Coordinators, 1981).
Bonds, Margaret, 1913-1972
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Music, 1930-1971. II. Other Papers, 1928-1983.
Margaret Bonds (1913-1972)
American composer, pianist, and teacher. Bonds's vocal music includes songs on texts of Langston Hughes, Countee Cullen, Edna St. Vincent Millay, and other poets, and arrangements of African American spirituals. In 1940, Bonds married Lawrence Richardson (1911-1990); they had a daughter, Djane Richardson (1946-2011).
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from William Reese Company (Doyle Books sale, New York, 2012 November 5, lot 152) on the Carl Van Vechten Fund and the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2012.
Scope and Contents
Vocal music, most 1960s or undated, consisting of autograph manuscript drafts and arrangements, transparencies, and diazo reproductions, some accompanied by copies of published music; and a small amount of other papers. Autograph manuscript music includes spirituals arranged for solo voice or chorus; The Negro Speaks of Rivers, Songs of the Seasons, Three Dream Portraits, and other songs on texts by Langston Hughes; songs on texts by Edna St. Vincent Millay and other poets; and musicals and songs with lyrics by Janice Lovoos, some with related correspondence. Other papers consist of a scrapbook containing photographs, clippings, and ephemera, most circa 1928-1930, some relating to Lincoln University, Pennsylvania, and Lawrence Richardson; and two books containing biographical information about Bonds and analysis of her music: Mildred Denby Green, Black Women Composers: A Genesis (Boston: Twayne Publishers, 1983), and Alice Tischler, Fifteen Black American Composers: A Bibliography of Their Works (Detroit: Information Coordinators, 1981).
African American Composers; Choral music -- Scores; Composers -- United States; Musicals -- Vocal scores with piano; Musicals -- Librettos; Song cycles; Songs with piano; Spirituals (Songs) -- United States; Women composers -- United States; Women composers, Black -- United States; Photographs -- United States -- 20th Century; Scrapbooks -- United States -- 20th Century; Composers -- United States -- 20th Century; Bonds, Margaret, 1913-1972; Hughes, Langston, 1902-1967 -- Musical settings; Lovoos, Janice; Lovoos, Janice -- Musical settings; Millay, Edna St. Vincent, 1892-1950 -- Musical settings; Richardson, Lawrence, 1911-1990; Lincoln University (Pa.) -- Students
- Oversize Music, 1930-1971, undated; Series I; 0.83; (10 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by work title.
  - African dance (SBar, piano), undated (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 1)
  - The Ballad of the Brown King (cantata)
    Related Materials
    See Box 11, folder 60
  - Bright Star (SATB, piano), undated (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 2)
    See also: Box 11, folder 61
  - Dem Bones (spiritual), undated (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 3)
  - Diary of a Divorcée (song cycle), undated (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 4)
  - Didn't It Rain (spiritual), c1966-1967 (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 5)
  - Don't Speak (song), undated (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 6)
  - Every Time I Feel the Spirit (spiritual), 1966, undated (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 7)
  - Ezek'el Saw the Wheel (spiritual), undated (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 8)
    See also: Box 11, Folder 62
  - Faith in Thee (song), undated (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 9)
  - Feast (song), undated (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 10)
  - Fields of Wonder (song cycle), undated (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 11)
    See also: Box 11, Folders 63-64
  - Five Spirituals (voice and orchestra), c1946, undated (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 12)
    See also: Box 11, Folder 65
  - Go Tell It on the Mountain (spiritual), 1959-c1966, undated (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 13)
    See also: Box 11, folders 66-67
  - Going for Water (song), 1962, undated (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 14)
  - Group Dance (voices, piano), undated (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 15)
  - Hand Me Down (spiritual), undated (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 16)
  - He Never Said a Mumbl'in' Word (spiritual), undated (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 17)
  - Hold On (spiritual), undated (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 18)
    See also: Box 11, folders 68-69
  - Hold the Wind (spiritual), undated (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 19)
  - How Strange (vocal music; fragment), undated (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 20)
  - Hyacinth (song), undated (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 21)
  - I Got a Home in that Rock (spiritual), c1968, undated (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 22)
  - I Know My Mind (song), undated (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 23)
    Scope and Contents
    Also titled "Sonnet II."
  - I Shall Pass Through this World (SATB, piano)
    See: Box 12, folders 70-71
  - I Talk With the Angels (song), c1967 (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 24)
  - I Want Jesus to Walk With Me (spiritual), undated (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 25)
  - I Wish I Knew How it Would Feel to be Free (spiritual), undated (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 26)
  - Joshua Fit Da Battle of Jericho (spiritual), c1966-1967, undated (Box 5 (Oversize), Folder 27)
  - Joy (SAT, string quartet, piano), undated (Box 5 (Oversize), Folder 28)
  - Lizzie (musical), c1968, 1971, undated (Box 5 (Oversize), Folder 29)
    About Elizabeth Keckley and Mary Todd Lincoln. With related letters from Janice Lovoos.
    See also: Box 12, folder 72
  - Los Angeles: Then and Now (musical), undated (Box 6 (Oversize), Folder 30)
    See also: Box 12, folder 73
  - Love's Runnin' Riot in My Bones (song), undated (Box 6 (Oversize), Folder 31)
  - The Negro Speaks of Rivers (song), undated (Box 6 (Oversize), Folder 32)
    See also: Box 12, folder 74
  - No Good Man (song), undated (Box 6 (Oversize), Folder 33)
  - The Pasture (song), 1930, undated (Box 6 (Oversize), Folder 34)
  - Peter, Go Ring Dem Bells (spiritual), undated (Box 7 (Oversize), Folder 35)
  - Pot Pourri (song cycle), 1968, undated (Box 7 (Oversize), Folder 36)
  - Rise Up Shepherd (spiritual), undated (Box 7 (Oversize), Folder 37)
  - Run Sinner Run (spiritual), undated (Box 7 (Oversize), Folder 38)
  - Sing Aho (spiritual), c1960, undated (Box 7 (Oversize), Folder 39)
  - Sinner, Please Don't Let This Harvest Pass (spiritual), undated (Box 8 (Oversize), Folder 40)
  - Sleep Song (SSAA, piano), undated (Box 8 (Oversize), Folder 41)
  - Songs of the Seasons (song cycle), undated (Box 8 (Oversize), Folder 42)
  - Sonnet: Even in the Moment (song), undated (Box 8 (Oversize), Folder 43)
  - Sonnet: What My Lips Have Kissed (song), undated (Box 8 (Oversize), Folder 44)
  - Sonnet: Women Have Loved Before (song), undated (Box 8 (Oversize), Folder 45)
  - Stan' Up an' Fight (song), undated (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 46)
  - Standin' in the Need of a Prayer (spiritual), 1966, undated (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 47)
  - Steady, Jesus Listenin' (spiritual), undated (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 48)
  - Stopping by Woods on a Snowy Evening (song), 1957, undated (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 49)
  - This Little Light of Mine (spiritual), 1969 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 50)
  - Three Dream Portraits (song cycle), undated (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 51)
  - To a Brown Girl, Dead (song), c1956, undated (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 52)
  - To One Who Might Have Borne a Message (song), undated (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 53)
  - Tropics After Dark (musical), undated (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 54)
  - Troubled Water (spiritual), undated (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 55)
  - We Shall Overcome (spiritual)
    See: Box 12, folder 75
  - Western Skies (song), undated (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 56)
  - When the Dove Enters In (song), undated (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 57)
  - Winter Night's Dream. Children's Sleep (children's opera), undated (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 58)
  - Unidentified fragments, 1962, undated (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 59)
- Other Music, 0.83; (2 boxes)
  - The Ballad of the Brown King (cantata), c1961 (Box 11, Folder 60)
  - Bright Star (SATB, piano), c1968 (Box 11, Folder 61)
  - Ezek'el Saw the Wheel (spiritual), c1966 (Box 11, Folder 62)
  - Fields of Wonder (song cycle), undated; 2 (Box 11, Folder 63-64)
  - Five Spirituals (voice and orchestra), c1964, undated (Box 11, Folder 65)
  - Go Tell It on the Mountain (spiritual), c1962; 2 (Box 11, Folder 66-67)
  - Hold On (spiritual), c1966; 2 (Box 11, Folder 68-69)
  - I Shall Pass Through this World (SATB, piano), c1967; 2 (Box 12, Folder 70-71)
  - Lizzie (musical), c1969 (Box 12, Folder 72)
  - Los Angeles: Then and Now (musical), undated (Box 12, Folder 73)
  - The Negro Speaks of Rivers (song), c1942 (Box 12, Folder 74)
  - We Shall Overcome (spiritual), undated (Box 12, Folder 75)
    Accompanied by a letter from Leontyne Price, 1969 November 12.
  - Lists of works, undated (Box 12, Folder 76)
- Other Papers, 1928-1983; Series II; 0.21; (1 box)
  - Scrapbook, 1928-1930, undated (Box 12, Folder 77)
  - Green, Mildred Denby. Black Women Composers: A Genesis (Boston: Twayne Publishers, 1983) (Box 13, Folder 78)
    Inscribed to "the Richardsons," undated
  - Tischler, Alice. Fifteen Black American Composers: A Bibliography of Their Works (Detroit: Information Coordinators, 1981) (Box 13, Folder 79)